Classes Collection UA039
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Classes Collection
1816 -- 2022
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Miller, Russell E.
UA039
52.41 Linear Feet 66 boxes, 10 oversized folders, 32 VHS cassette tapes
2 Volumes
11 Digital Object(s) Of the 11 digital objects in this collection, 2 have extent information comprising 18 files.
56.0 Megabytes Of the 11 digital objects in this collection, 2 have extent information comprising 67.7 MB.
This collection contains memorabilia and other material relating to various graduating classes from Tufts University.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in two series: Classes, and Additional accessions.
Material is added to the collection as it relates to graduating classes, so it is organized by class year, not date of the creation of the material. For example, a 50th reunion book for the class of 1928 would be in the series for the class of 1928, and not with material created in 1978.
Biographical / Historical
Russell Elliott Miller was a Professor of History, University Historian and Archivist of Tufts University, and author of "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952" and the second volume "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts University since 1952." He was born in Bloomington, Minnesota, on April 25, 1916, to one of the last pioneer families in the Minnesota prairie. His mother spoke Dakota Sioux, which she had learned as a child. He received a B.A. in Education in 1937 and an M.A. in political science in 1939, both from the University of Florida at Gainesville. From 1942 to 1946, he served in the Army Air Corps as an enlisted man, rising to the rank of technical sergeant. Initially with personnel and classification, he was finally assigned to the historical section (intelligence) at the headquarters of the troop carrier command. In 1948 he earned a Master of Arts in history from Princeton University and came to Tufts that same year.
In 1952 he received a PhD from Princeton, and in 1964 Tufts appointed him Professor of History and University Historian and archivist. He taught courses ranging from the history of western civilization to the history of the American frontier. In 1966, he published "Light on the Hill, A History of Tufts College from 1852 to 1952." That year he received the Distinguished Service Award from the Tufts Alumni Association and became an honorary member of Phi Beta Kappa. In 1975 he became the Walter S. Dickson Professor of English and American History and chaired the Department of History from then until 1980. He was voted Emeritus Professor of English and American History in 1981 and received an honorary Doctor of Letters degree in 1983. In 1986, he completed the second volume of Tufts history, "Light on the Hill II, A History of Tufts University since 1952."
Custodial History
The Classes collection was created by Russell Miller to organize material relating to individual classes that did not fit into any of his other subject categories. Material about individual classes is currently added to the collection.
All material accessioned prior to 1997 was originally arranged by subject, no attempt was made to recreate original order, although material relating to administering the collection was removed to the documentation files of the collection in the archives.
Most of the news clippings, photographs, press releases, and correspondence have been separated from the subject files. These types of materials are present however, throughout the subject files as well.
Related Materials
Jackson College for Women Records, 1871-1985. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains reunion notes and programs, class day and class activity books, scrapbooks, graduation ceremony records, and photographs of graduated classes from 1858 on. The collection also includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, audio and video recordings, and memorabilia such as graduation gowns, class rings, pins, and patches related to graduated classes.
Tufts University -- History; Student life; Student activities; Alumni and Alumni Relations
- Classes, 1816 -- 2022; 1857 -- 2000; UA039.001; 32.45 Linear Feet; 2 Volumes; 10 Digital Object(s) Of the 10 digital objects in this series, 2 have extent information comprising 18 files.; 56.0 Megabytes Of the 10 digital objects in this series, 2 have extent information comprising 67.7 MB.
  Scope and Contents
  The "Classes" collection was created by Russell Miller to organize material relating to individual classes that did not fit into any of his other subject categories. Material about individual classes is currently added to the collection. This collection contains reunion notes and programs, class day and class activity books, scrapbooks, and newspaper clippings of classes from 1858. Material is added to the collection as it relates to graduating classes, so it is organized by class year, not date of the creation of the material. For example, a 50th reunion book of the class of 1928, would be in the series of that class, and not with material created in 1978.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically into groups by graduating class year.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Unknown class, 1950 -- 1985; UA039.001.001
    - "For Jumbo" Pin, UA039.001.018.00002 (Box 18)
      White and Blue pin featuring Jumbo bearing a "T" and "For Jumbo" written around the edge. Donor unknown. No Date Available
    - "For Jumbo" Pin, UA039.001.018.00003 (Box 18)
      White and Blue pin featuring Jumbo bearing a "T" and "For Jumbo" written around the edge. The initials "R.R." are written in green pen on the pin. Donor unknown. No Date Available
    - "Tufts College Jumbo Bonds" Pin, UA039.001.018.00004 (Box 18)
      Brown and blue pin featuring Jumbo's head and "Tufts College Jumbo Bonds;" donor unknown. No Date Available
    - "Tufts College Jumbo Bonds" Pin, UA039.001.018.00005 (Box 18)
      Brown and blue pin featuring Jumbo's head and "Tufts College Jumbo Bonds;" the needle to the pin is missing;donor unknown. No Date Available
    - "Tufts College Jumbo Bonds" Pin, UA039.001.018.00006 (Box 18)
      Brown and blue pin featuring Jumbo's head and "Tufts College Jumbo Bonds;"donor unknown. No Date Available
    - 'T' Medal made of Bronze, UA039.001.018.00011 (Box 18)
      It unknown what this was used for; appears to be a medal made of bronze featuring a large 'T;' donated by Donna Hersey Sandin. No Date Available
    - Tufts Card Holder, UA039.001.018.00012 (Box 18)
      Metal card holder with Tufts Seal in the center; donated by Donna Hersey Sandin. No Date Available
    - Red and Black Pennant with number "15", UA039.001.073.00001 (Box 73)
      Donor and use unknown; possibly used for Athletic Meets or as a Class Pennant; severely damaged by moths. No Date Available
    - Blue and Yellow Pennant with number "16", UA039.001.073.00002 (Box 73)
      Donor and use unknown; possibly used for Athletic Meets or as a Class Pennant; damaged by moths. No Date Available
    - Red and White Pennant with number "17", UA039.001.073.00003 (Box 73)
    - Brown and Blue sash or armband with a "T" in the center, UA039.001.073.00004 (Box 73)
      Donor and use unknown; possibly used for Athletic Meets; damaged by moths. No Date Available
    - Music pendent, UA039.001.073.00006 (Box 73)
      Found uncataloged in the stacks in Winter 2009. Could perhaps be a souvenir of a Tufts music club. No Date Available
    - Unidentified class beanie, UA039.001.073.00007 (Box 73)
      Found uncataloged in the stacks in Winter 2009. No Date Available
    - 50th Reunion pin with ribbon, 1950 -- 1985; UA039.001.078.00008 (Box 78)
      Donated by Donna H. Sandin. Exact date is unknown.
    - Reunion, outside, aerial view, 1950 -- 1960; UA039.001.080.00016 (Box Shared 38)
      It is unclear what classes are in attendance. The dates are approximate.
  - Classes of 1858-1869, 1855 -- 1869; UA039.001.002
    - Classes, 1858; UA039.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
      Catalogue 1854-1855 of Tufts College from Mr. A. E. Scott (A'1858) was added in Jan./2009. Program, Tufts College First Freshman Supper; program, Junior Class at Tufts College.
      - Second Irregular Commencement of Tough College, 1858-06-14; UA039.001.001.00001.00002 (Box 1)
        A satire commencement program put out by the class of 1858.
        Medford (Mass.); Commencement ceremonies; Satire.; Wit and humor; programs (documents); Tufts College
    - Classes, 1859; UA039.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
      J. Wight student notebooks located in 39090014012492. Program, Annual Exhibition of the Junior Class of Tufts College; correspondences. Catalogue 1858-1859, marked in the catalogue are those students who were either absent or deferred from the College for the year academic year.
    - Classes, 1860; UA039.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
      Program, suggestions to the class of sixty; John Wilkes Hammond's term bill, January 11, 1860, donated by great grandson Henry Hammond in April 2006. John Wilkes Hammond attended Tufts from 1856-1860. He marreid Clara Tweed, daughter of Tufts Professor Benjamin Franklin Tweed. Mr. Hammond later on served on the Massachusetts Superior Court and on the Supreme Judicial Court (1898-1913).
    - Classes, 1861; UA039.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
      Program, the Tufts College Third Freshman Supper; correspondences.
    - Classes, 1862; UA039.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
      Program, the Tufts College Junior Exhibition.
    - Classes, 1863; UA039.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
      Program, Tufts College Junior Exhibition; program, Tufts College Freshman Supper; drafted resolutions.
    - Classes, 1864; UA039.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
      Program, Tufts College Junior Exhibition; program, Annual Exhibition.
    - Classes, 1865; UA039.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
      Program, Pow-Wow of the Class of '65; program, Annual Exhibition; hand-written song book.
    - Classes, 1866; UA039.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
      Class records; program, Tufts College Freshman Supper; hand written program, Tufts College Freshman Supper; correspondence
    - Classes, 1867; UA039.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
      Class records; program, Annual Exhibition of the Junior Class at Tufts College; program, Tufts College Freshman Supper, program, Annual Exhibition at Tufts College; correspondence
    - Classes, 1868; UA039.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
      Minutes of the Freshman Council, class of 1868.
    - Classes, 1869; UA039.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
      Program, Annual Exhibition at Tufts College; program, Tufts College Freshman Supper.
    - White, William P. A 1866 [Essay for Latin Prize Competition], UA039.001.001.00034 (Box 1)
      Two copies. Material in this file was pulled from Russell Miller's vertical files in Fall 2009.
    - Student photographs poster, 1857; UA039.001.001.00035 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 1)
      The assembled photograph poster is very fragile. Needs conservation work.
    - Faculty photographs poster, 1857; UA039.001.001.00036 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 1)
    - Mug; The Order of the Coffeepot, 1858; UA039.001.018.00001 (Box 18)
    - Class of 1869 photographs, UA039.001.050.00001 (Box 50)
    - Jarvis S. Wight latin prose notebook, 1855 -- 1859; UA039.001.075.00001 (Box 75)
    - Jarvis S. Wight greek prose notebook, 1855 -- 1859; UA039.001.075.00002 (Box 75)
  - Classes of 1870-1879, 1816 -- 1929; UA039.001.003
    - Classes, 1870 -- 1874; UA039.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
      Rules and regulations of Tufts College; "The Burial of Analytics, Tufts College" (student hoax).
    - Classes, 1875; UA039.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
      Correspondence
    - Classes, 1876; UA039.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
      Dance card; program, Class day; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1877; UA039.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
      Program and invitation, Class Day.
    - Classes, 1878; UA039.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
      Invitation, Class Day; program, Class Day.
    - Classes, 1879; UA039.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
      Program, Class Day; program, commencement; program, Class Day; Tuition bills (Donated by Donna Hersey Sandin)
    - Class of 1870 photographs, UA039.001.050.00002 (Box 50)
    - Class of 1873 photographs, UA039.001.050.00003 (Box 50)
    - Class of 1874 photographs, UA039.001.050.00004 (Box 50)
    - Class of 1876 photographs, 1816; UA039.001.050.00005 (Box 50)
    - Class of 1879 photographs, 1879 -- 1929; UA039.001.050.00006 (Box 50)
  - Classes of 1880-1889, 1880 -- 1950; UA039.001.004
    - Classes, 1880; UA039.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
      Program, concert; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1882; UA039.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
      Program, Class Day; program, concert; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1883; UA039.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
    - Classes, 1884; UA039.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
      correspondence
    - Classes, 1885; UA039.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
      Photo, list, 50th reunion.
    - Classes, 1886; UA039.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
      Class song; program, Class Day; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1887; UA039.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
      Menu; program, Class Day; correspondence; program, Quinquennial; catalogue.
    - Classes, 1888; UA039.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
    - Classes, 1889; UA039.001.001.00027 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1881 photographs, 1931; UA039.001.050.00007 (Box 50)
    - Class of 1883 photographs, 1933 -- 1950; UA039.001.051.00001 (Box 51)
    - Class of 1884 photographs, 1884 -- 1939; UA039.001.051.00002 (Box 51)
    - Class of 1885 photographs, 1885 -- 1940; UA039.001.051.00003 (Box 51)
    - Class of 1886 photographs, UA039.001.051.00004 (Box 51)
    - Class of 1887 photographs, 1883; UA039.001.051.00005 (Box 51)
      - Freshman Class of 1887, 1883-09; UA039.001.051.00005.00001; Unknown (Box 51)
        Identified below photograph: Alva Edson Snow, William Andrew Woodward, George Albert Chapin, James Francis Albion, George Austin Bailey, Leo Rich Lewis, Thomas Goddard Frothingham, Frank Elliott Bateman, John Garibaldi Sargent, John Douglass Merrill, Stephen Austin Foster, David Addison Cook, Nelson Pingry Cook, Willis James Prouty, David Lee Maulsby, Waldo Lincoln Cook, Wilson Lincoln Fairbanks, Charles H. Patterson.
        Students; Portraits, Group; Lewis, Leo R.; Maulsby, David Lee
    - Tufts College athletics and classes photographs, 1880 -- 1941; UA039.001.081.00001 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 6)
      Photograph of Tufts College football team, 1880-1900. These dates are approximate. Photograph of Tufts College, Medford, Ma, November 14, 1941. Photograph taken by Rov D. Young Studio, Mount Vernon, Iowa. Original pastel sketch football poster--Tufts Athletic Field, Bates vs. Tufts, 3 P.M. Oct. 3, 1914, by Geyendecker (item found uncataloged in the stacks in the spring of 2009).
    - Tufts College Class of 1881, UA039.001.DO.00124; Unknown (Box Shared 27)
      Possibly Class of 1882. There are two copies of this image.
      People; Students; Portraits, Group
  - Classes of 1890-1899, 1891 -- 1940; UA039.001.005
    - Classes, 1891; UA039.001.001.00028 (Box 1)
      Program, Class Day; program, reunion; invitation, Class Day, correspondence.
    - Classes, 1892; UA039.001.001.00029 (Box 1)
      Class records; newspaper clippings; program, Class Day; invitation, CLass Day; dance card, Junior Promenade; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1893; UA039.001.001.00030 (Box 1)
      Newspaper clippings; program, Class Day; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1894; UA039.001.001.00031 (Box 1)
      Program, Class Day; invitation, Class Day; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1895; UA039.001.001.00032 (Box 1)
      Newspaper clippings; program, Class Day; program, fortieth annual dinner; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1896; UA039.001.001.00033 (Box 1)
      Newspaper clippings, program, anniversary; program, Class day; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1897; UA039.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
      Program, Class Day; newspaper clippings.
    - Classes, 1898; UA039.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
      Newspaper clippings; menu, commencement dinner; program, Class Day; program, commencement; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1899; UA039.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
      Newspaper clippings; program, Class Day; invitation, Class Day; correspondence; decennial register; quindecennial register; invitation, Freshman Banquet.
    - Class of 1890 photographs, 1940; UA039.001.051.00006 (Box 51)
    - Class of 1892 photographs, 1892 -- 1927; UA039.001.051.00007 (Box 51)
    - Class of 1892 photographs, 1912; UA039.001.051.00008 (Box 51)
    - Records of the Class of 1892, 1912; UA039.001.051.00009 (Box 51)
      Scrapbook kept by John Murray Hollister A'92 about his class covering the years of 1892 to 1960. Also included is letter about donation by his daughter Ruth H. Howard in 1963.
    - Class of 1895 photographs, UA039.001.052.00001 (Box 52)
    - Class of 1896 photographs, UA039.001.052.00002 (Box 52)
    - Class of 1898 photographs, 1920; UA039.001.052.00003 (Box 52)
    - Class of 1895, UA039.001.052.00007 (Box Shared 4)
      This photograph was found uncatalogued in the stacks in summer 2007. Note its different location; it is housed in a separate box with other oversize materials.
    - Tufts College, class of 1891, UA039.001.080.00006 (Box Shared 38)
    - Tufts College reunion, class of 1892, UA039.001.080.00008 (Box Shared 38)
    - White, Winthrop W. A1897 [Predictions of his classmates' futures], UA039.001.084.00003 (Box 84)
      White's predictions of the lives his classmates would lead after leaving Tufts in 1897. Material in this file was pulled from Russell Miller's vertical files in Fall 2009.
    - Atwood, Louise R. wa 1897 [Notebook], UA039.001.084.00004 (Box 84)
      Possibly minutes or notes of the Women's Club at Tufts. Material relates primarily to American literature, specifically famous authors, literary criticism, and literary periods. The beginning of the notebook also includes notes regarding King Ferdinand and Queen Isabella of Spain. Material in this file was pulled from Russell Miller's vertical files in Fall 2009.
  - Classes of 1900-1909, 1900 -- 1968; UA039.001.006
    - Classes, 1900; UA039.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
      Program, Class Day; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1901; UA039.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
      Program, Class Day; "cheers of 1903"; Tufts song book.
    - Classes, 1902; UA039.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
      Invitation, program, Class Day; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1903; UA039.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
      Program, Class Day; Class Day music; Class Day cheers; the Nineteen-Three Club; correspondence; "History of the Class of 1903" by Harry Adams Hersey (Donated by Donna Hersey Sandin).
    - Classes, 1904; UA039.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
      Dance card; ticket, Class Day; constitution and bylaws of the Tufts 1904 Club; I and II annual reports, Tufts 1904 Club; music, Class Day; cheers and songs, Class Day; class letters; newspaper clippings; photos; program, 50th reunion.
    - Classes, 1907; UA039.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
      Programs, Class Day; "History of the Class of 1907"; correspondence; 1907 Tufts calendar.
    - Classes, 1908; UA039.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
      Newspaper clippings; ticket, program, music, Class Day; calendar, correspondence.
    - Classes (2 of 2), 1908; UA039.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
      Program, Class Day.
    - Classes, 1909; UA039.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
      Class calandar; name tag; program, invitation, music, Class Day; class song; alumni Field Day bulletin; correspondence.
    - Classes, "Here and There at Tufts", 1909; UA039.001.014.001 (Box Volume 14)
      "Here and There at Tufts", publication.
    - Gold and Brown 1902 Pin, UA039.001.018.00008 (Box 18)
      Pin is engraved on the back with "B.C.H.;" also engraved on the front with "ES;" pin donated by Donna Hersey Sandin
    - "Tufts College A.A." Second Place Medal for Pole Vaulting, 1909, UA039.001.018.00010 (Box 18)
      The medal was won by Prentice Williams Towsley Class of 1910 Engineering; it appears to be made of bronze; it was donated by Donna Hersey Sandin
    - Class of 1900 photographs, UA039.001.052.00004 (Box 52)
    - Class of 1901 photographs, 1931 -- 1968; UA039.001.052.00005 (Box 52)
    - Class of 1902-03 photographs, 1902 -- 1948; UA039.001.052.00006 (Box 52)
    - Class of 1904 photographs, 1924 -- 1964; UA039.001.053.00001 (Box 53)
    - Class of 1905 photographs, 1955; UA039.001.053.00002 (Box 53)
    - Class of 1909 photographs, 1954 -- 1959; UA039.001.053.00003 (Box 53)
    - Medical School Classes, 1907-1926, UA039.001.065.00004 (Box Shared 66)
      Located in UIP Box 88 oversized photos.
    - Tufts College Alumni and Classes, Photographs, 1909 -- 1948; UA039.001.077.00001 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 5)
      Most of these items were found uncatalogued in the stacks in the summer of 2007. Tufts College Alumni Field Day, June 15, 1909; Class of 1941 (2 copies); Tufts College, Class of 1914; Tufts-Jackson College, Class of 1934; Tufts College, Class of 1912; Graduate Class, Tufts College, Class of 1927 (2 copies); Tufts College Alumni, June 20, 1911; Tufts College Medical School, Class of 1948 (found at fleamarket, 9/25/05).
    - Studio portrait, men in suits and ties, 1908 -- 1909; UA039.001.080.00002 (Box Shared 38)
      It is unclear if this is the class of 1908-1909.
    - Studio portrait, men in suits and ties, 1909 -- 1910; UA039.001.080.00003 (Box Shared 38)
      It is unclear if this is the class of 1909-1910.
    - Last sing, 1909-05; UA039.001.080.00014 (Box Shared 38)
    - Classes, 1905; UA039.001.084.00001 (Box 84)
      Program, Class Day; music, Class Day; tickets, Class day; program, Semi-Centennial; invitation, The Semi-Centennial Tufts College book, 50th Anniversary of Tufts College; class song, 1905; class calandar; correspondence.
    - Classes, 1906; UA039.001.084.00002 (Box 84)
      Class calandar; dance card; newspaper clippings; program, First Banquet and Assembly; music and invitation, Class Day; program, Class day; correspondence.
    - Co-ed student body, 1902; UA039.001.DO.00126; Unknown (Box Shared 26)
      25. This date is approximate.
      Students; Women; Portraits, Group
    - Norbert Wiener portrait, circa 1911; UA039.000512; 3 Linear Feet (Object 88)
  - Classes of 1910-1919, 1908 -- 1972; UA039.001.007
    - Classes (1), 1910; UA039.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
      Newspaper clippings; program, Junior Day; program, Class Day; program, Sophmore Banquet; class song; correspondence; 1910 Tufts calendar.
    - Classes (2), 1910; UA039.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
      Members of the class of 1910.
    - Classes (3), 1910; UA039.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
      Class letters v.1; program, Class Day; Jackson College 50th Anniversary.
    - Classes (4), 1910; UA039.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
      25th Reunion "Class Letters and History"; program, 30th Reunion; report of reunion; meeting minutes, class of 1910; notes.
    - Classes (5), 1910; UA039.001.003.00009 (Box 3)
      Prentice Williams Towsley's Junior Banquet program; Class Day program-donated by Donna Sandin (2009.086)
    - Classes, 1911; UA039.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
      Newspaper clippings; program, Junior Day; farcical newsreport; music, Class Day; program, 50th reunion; correspondence; class letters.
    - Classes (2 of 2), 1911; UA039.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
      Program, Class Day; Calendar.
    - Classes, 1912; UA039.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
      Class letters; newspaper clippings; invitation, commencement; 50th reunion; also includes a photocopy of the cover of the 1912 Tufts calendar.
    - Classes, 1912; UA039.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
      Music, Class day; program, Tufts Senior Banquet; program, Tufts Junior Day; programs, First and Second Annual Banquets for the Class of 1912.
    - Classes (3), 1912; UA039.001.004.00005 (Box 4)